# PABLO VILLANUEVA DOMINGO

## PHD IN PHYSICS & DEEP LEARNING SCIENTIST

I obtained my **PhD in theoretical physics** at the University of València, Spain, researching **deep learning** techniques in cosmology and astrophysics. During my PhD, I led international collaborations, published scientific articles and presented the results in multiple seminars. Currently, I am working as **deep learning scientist** in the autonomous driving simulator project CARLA.

### **CONTACT**

- Pablo.Villanueva.Domingo@gmail.com
- pablovd.github.io
- @PabloVD
- in pablo-villanueva-domingo-76b6491b2
- **(D)** 0000-0002-0936-4279
- Pablo Villanueva Domingo
- @CosmoPabloVD

### **SKILLS**

### Computation

### **Programming languages**

Python, C, C++, C#, Fortran, SQL

#### General software

Git, Docker, LaTeX, MATLAB, Mathematica

#### Data analysis

Numpy, SciPy, Pandas, OpenCV, Networkx

### Visualization

Matplotlib, Seaborn, Plotly, Folium

### 3D engines

Basics of Unreal, Godot, Unity

## **Autonomous driving software**

Carla, ROS2

### Simulation software

Chrono, Flex

### Web development

HTML, CSS, Javascript, Jekyll, Flask

## Machine learning

### **ML libraries**

PyTorch, TensorFlow, PyTorch Lightning, PyTorch Geometric, Scikit-learn, ONNX

### Neural Nets experience

Graph (GNNs), Convolutional (CNNs), U-Nets, Diffusion models, GANs, LSTMs

## Fields

Computer vision, Natural Language Processing, Reinforcement Learning

## See my work in ML and programming at

https://pablovd.github.io/codes

### Soft skills

### Communication

Public speaking, writing skills

### **Project management**

Collaboration, teamwork, initiative, organization

## **Problem solving**

Logical reasoning, lateral thinking, creativity, data modeling

### **A**■ Languages

SpanishMother tongueCatalanMother tongueEnglishFluentPortugueseBasics

## **WORK HISTORY**

- Deep Learning Scientist
- iii Jan. 2022- Now | ♥ Computer Vision Center Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona Data-driven traffic models, Al behavior agents, neural terramechanics and computer vision at the autonomous driving simulator CARLA
- Research assistant
- i Jun. 2021- Dec. 2021 | ▼ Instituto de Física Corpuscular Universitat de València Técnico superior de apoyo a la investigación, CIDEGENT/2018/019, CPI-21-108
- PhD fellowship
- Research introduction fellowship
- May-Oct. 2016 | ▼ Instituto de Física Corpuscular Iniciación a la investigación Severo Ochoa

## **EDUCATION**

- PhD in Physics, cum laude
- **i** 2016-2021 | **v** Instituto de Física Corpuscular Universitat de València
- Master in Advanced Physics
- **i** 2015-2016 | ♥ Universitat de València
- Bachelor of Physics
- **=** 2011-2015 | ♥ Universitat de València

As well as multiple PhD schools and courses which can be found here.

## **→** RESEARCH STAYS

I have led several international research collaborations, visiting universities from different countries:

- ii Nov.- Dec. 2019 | ▼ 3 weeks at Service de Physique Théorique, Université Libre de Bruxelles, Brussels, Belgium.
- **■** Sep.- Oct. 2019 | **●** 1 month at Department of Astrophysical Sciences, Princeton University, New Jersey, USA.
- **i** Sep.- Nov. 2018 |  **•** 2 months at Kavli IPMU, University of Tokyo, Japan.
- **i** Jun.- Aug. 2017 |  **•** 2 months at Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory (Fermilab), Illinois, USA.

## **T** AWARDS

- Feb. 2023 | CSIC 2021 relevant PhD Thesis Award, by Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Científicas (CSIC).
- Dec. 2016 | 1st prize in the XXVII edición del Premio Rotary al Fomento del Trabajo Experimental en Física.

## **TALKS**

I have given **9 seminars** at the universities of Princeton (USA), Tokyo, Nagoya (Japan), Brussels and València; as well as **8 talks** in conferences, meetings and schools.

A complete list can be found at https://pablovd.github.io/talks.pdf These are some selected talks:

- Neural Terramechanics and the RACER-SIM project
- **i** Jul. 28 2022 | ♥ EAI Tech Forum, Intel Labs, online
- Weighing the Milky Way with AI
- **i** Jan. 17 2022 | **♥** Cosmology Talks, online (Youtube channel) | Video
- Machine Learning at galactic and cosmological scales
- Nov. 17 2021 | ¶ Instituto de Física Corpuscular | Video and slides

## **SELECTED PUBLICATIONS**

I have published **21 scientific articles** in high impact journals based on my research on cosmology and astrophysics. The full list of publications can be found in my INSPIRE profile P.Villanueva.Domingo.1. I have applied **deep learning** methods in part of my research, such as in the following works:

• Weighing the Milky Way and Andromeda with Artificial Intelligence

**Pablo Villanueva-Domingo**, Francisco Villaescusa-Navarro, Shy Genel, Daniel Anglés-Alcázar, Lars Hernquist, Federico Marinacci, David N. Spergel, Mark Vogelsberger and Desika Narayanan

■ Nov. 2021 | ■ Physical Review D 107, 103003, 2023, arXiv:2111.14874

The total masses of the Milky Way and Andromeda galaxies are predicted using AI for the first time, via Graph Neural Networks.

Inferring halo masses with Graph Neural Networks

**Pablo Villanueva-Domingo**, Francisco Villaescusa-Navarro, Daniel Anglés-Alcázar, Shy Genel, Federico Marinacci, David N. Spergel, Lars Hernquist, Mark Vogelsberger, Romeel Dave and Desika Narayanan

**★** Nov. 2021 | **★** The Astrophysical Journal, Volume 935(1):30, 2022, arXiv:2111.08683

Graph Neural Networks in PyTorch Geometric are trained in simulations to infer the mass of dark matter halos.

• Removing Astrophysics in 21 cm maps with Neural Networks

Pablo Villanueva-Domingo and Francisco Villaescusa-Navarro

**Jan. 2021** | **II** The Astrophysical Journal, 907(1):44, 2021; arXiv:2006.14305

The cosmic density field is predicted from maps of distribution of hydrogen training a U-Net in PyTorch.

## OUTREACH & ADDITIONAL WORK EXPERIENCE

- 苗 Feb. 2021 | Outreach video about the astronomer Sandra M. Faber within the project Pioneras Recordando a Lise Meitner.
- 苗 2020 Now | Journal referee for journals such as MNRAS and ApJ. See reviews in my Publons profile
- Jun. 2019 | Member of the local organizing committee of the Invisibles19 Workshop at València and Invisibles19 School at Laboratorio subterráneo de Canfranc (LSC)
- 苗 2016-2017 | Collaboration in the organization of the outreach event Feria-Concurso Experimenta, València.

### **REFERENCES**

- Dr. Olga Mena Requejo
- ☆ Instituto de Física corpuscular, CSIC | omena@ific.uv.es
- Dr. Francisco Villaescusa Navarro
- 🖍 Center for Computational Astrophysics, Flatiron Institute, New York | 💌 villaescusa.francisco@gmail.com
- Dr. Sergio Palomares Ruiz
- ☆ Instituto de Física corpuscular, CSIC | Sergio.Palomares.Ruiz@ific.uv.es
- Dr. Laura Lopez Honorez
- ↑ Université Libre de Bruxelles, Vrije Universiteit Brussel | 
  □ llopezho@ulb.ac.be